Five Years Ago, May
This year, I'll see you at nationals.
(烏養)今年こそは全国大会でな
Heh! You say the same thing every year.
(猫又)
ふそれ毎年言てるけどな
Shaddup!
(烏養)うせぇ今年こそだよ
This is gonna be the year.
We're looking forward to the Battle of the Garbage Dumpster at nationals this year!
(観客)今年こそ
全国大会でのゴミ捨て場の決戦
楽しみにしてるぞ
(武田･ﾅﾚｰｼｮﾝ)＜だが
６月のインタハイ予選では
But at the June interhigh, both schools
narrowly miss earning a ticket to nationals.
両校は惜しくも出場を逃す＞
＜翌年３月
In March of the next year, Karasuno High, representing Miyagi prefecture,
烏野高校は宮城代表として
and Nekoma High, as Tokyo's second representative,
音駒高校は東京第２代表として
春の高校バレ全国大会に
出場するが
both appeared in the Spring High School
National Volleyball Tournament, however...
烏野は３回戦で敗れ
Karasuno was defeated in the third round,
and Nekoma was eliminated in the quarterfinals.
音駒も準々決勝で敗退＞
They held many, many practice matches,
＜幾度となく
練習試合を重ねても
but both coaches retired without ever
crossing swords in an official capacity.
公式の舞台で兵刃を交えることは
一度もかなわぬまま
両監督は引退＞
This led to the steady decline of both teams.
＜それを機に両チムは
衰退の一途をたどることとなる＞
Karasuno High School Volleyball Team
＜しかし今＞
But now...
＜因縁の再戦開始＞
Let the fateful rematch begin!
Episode Twelve:
The Cat and Crow Reunion
≫研磨
Kenma!
駒だたの
(孤爪)あうん
Y-Y-You go to Nekoma?!
Uh, yeah.
なんで
教えてくんなかたんだよ
How come you didn't tell me?
You never asked.
だて聞かれてない
う
でもあのときまたねて言た
何か知てたんだろ
But you said, "See you later"!
You must've known something!
(孤爪)Ｔシャツに
｢KARASUNOHIGHSCHOOL｣て
The words "Karasuno High School" were on your T-shirt.
書いてあたから
(山本)ヘイヘイヘイ
Hey, hey, hey!
うちのセタに
なんの用ですか
What business do you have with our setter?
い
ちょと
Hey.
I-I'm sorry!
ごごめんなさあ
(田中)そちこそ
What about you?
うちの１年に
なんの用ですかこら
What business do you have with our first-year? Eh?
なんだこら
やんのかこらシテｨボイこら
What's it to you?
You wanna rumble, city boy? Eh?
(菅原)｢やんのか｣てやるんだろ
これから試合なんだから
You're about to rumble in the match we're about to play.
あとシティボイとかやめろ
恥ずかしい
And stop saying "city boy." It's embarrassing.
Yamamoto, stop picking fights all the time.
(夜久)山本お前
すぐケンカ吹かけんのやめろ
バカに見えるから
It makes you look stupid.
なんかすみません
恥ずかしいヤツいて
I apologize on behalf of my embarrassing teammate.
(菅原)うちもすみません
お恥ずかしい
I apologize for mine as well. I'm very embarrassed.
はうあ
(田中)え
女子マネジャ美
(芝山)やた
Female manager... Good!
Right on!
They have a female manager! Yakisoba bun score!
(犬岡)女子マネジャいた
(２人)焼きそばパンゲト
覚えてろよ
You'll pay for this!
(犬岡)あ猛虎さん逃げないで
Taketora, stand your ground!
(影山飛雄)お前なんで
向こうのヤツと知り合いなんだよ
Why do you know one of them personally?
駒のセタだて
I happened to run into him while we were out jogging.
He's Nekoma's setter.
Setter?
セタ
うお
(黒尾)
今日はよろしくお願いします
I'm looking forward to our match today.
(澤村)こちらこそ
よろしくお願いします
I'm also looking forward to our match today.
Woo-hoo! The ceiling is so high!
ほぉ天井高ぇ
別に普通だろ
Hold that end.
It's just a ceiling.
≪あ
こいつ食えないタイプのヤツだ≫
Oh, he's the shrewd type.
It's been eight years.
(直井)８年ぶりか
なんだよ烏養その頭
What's the deal with your hair, Ukai?
(繋心)うせぇ直井
お前は変わんなすぎだろ
Shaddup, Naoi. You should try something new for a change!
(２人)へへ
(猫又)おう繋心か
Hey, Keishin!
(繋心)
あお久しぶりです猫又先生
It's been a long time, Mr. Nekomata!
相変わらず
じじいそくりの顔しやがて
I see you still have the face the old man gave you.
(武田)
おお電話した武田です
I'm Takeda! We spoke on the phone.
今日はわざわざ
本当にありがとうございます
Thank you for going out of your way today.
(猫又)そりゃあんなにしつこく
電話もらたらねぇ
It's hard to ignore all those phone calls.
来ないわけには
(武田)すすいません
I had to respond.
Forgive me!
(猫又)冗談です冗談
I'm only kidding.
うちもこの３日
いい練習試合ができました
We had ourselves some good
practice matches in the last three days.
今日もよろしくお願いします
(武田)はいこちらこそ
Thank you for the match.
Yes, sir! Thank you!
相手が烏養のじじいじゃなくとも
And I don't care if you're not the old man.
容赦しねぇよ
I'll show you no mercy.
(澤村)正直言て俺たちは
To be honest,
顔合わせたばかで
デコボコでちぐはぐで
we've only just met, and we're still awkward and uncoordinated.
しかも
今日がこのメンツで初試合だ
Plus, this is our first match using these members.
音駒という未知のチム相手に
I don't know what kind of wall we'll be up against with Nekoma.
どんな壁に
ぶち当たるか分からない
でも壁にぶち当たたときは
But once we are up against that wall...
それを越えるチャンスだ
that will be our chance to rise above it!
(黒尾)俺たちは血液だ
We are plasma.
滞りなく流れろ酸素を回せ
Keep the flow in motion.
Distribute the oxygen so the brain can run smoothly!
脳が正常に働くために
行くぞ
(一同)あす
Let's go!
Yes, sir!
(孤爪)クロ今のやめない
なんか恥ずかしい
Kuro, can you stop doing that?
It's kind of embarrassing.
(山本)
いいじゃねぇか雰囲気雰囲気
What's wrong with it?! It's for atmosphere.
(海)
自分らへの暗示みたいなもんだ
It's like self-hypnosis.
ということだ
Exactly.
(滝ノ上)お間に合た
We made it!
Line up!
It's been a long time since the last Battle of the Garbage Dumpster.
(嶋田)
久々だねぇゴミ捨て場の決戦
駒高校対烏野高校の
We will now commence the practice match between Nekoma High and Karasuno High!
練習試合を始めます
(一同)よろしくお願いします
Let's have a good match!
(澤村)今日は緊張してないな
はい
You aren't nervous today.
Yes, sir.
You're tiny!
なななめんなよ
なめてねぇよ全然
D-Don't you mock me!
I'm not mocking you in the slightest!
ほほんとに
おう
R-Really?
Yeah!
Tch.
ち
(２人)う
He could at least let his guard down.
≪ちょとぐらい油断しろや
この野郎≫
翔陽俺
Shouyou.
I know I said that I think I have a pretty good team...
うちのチム
強いと思うて言たけど
強いのは俺じゃなくて
but I'm not good.
みんなだから
We all are.
ん
(黒尾)研磨ナイサ
(西谷)旭さん
Give us a nice serve, Kenma!
Asahi!
(東峰)
オライすまんちょい短い
Got it!
I'm sorry. It was too short!
(西谷)
旭さん１か月もサボるから
It's your fault for skipping a whole month!
I'm sorry!
(東峰)すいません
(澤村)影山カバ
Kageyama, cover it!
Right!
That was really fast.
すげぇ速ぇ何
What was that?
あんなとこから速攻
A fast attack from that far away?
なんだありゃ
トス見てねぇじゃねぇか
What was that? He didn't even look at the set.
(２人)ふふ
That's amazing.
(孤爪)すごいねびくりした
えへへへ
I'm surprised.
(西谷)ナイス翔陽
あざす
Good job, Shouyou!
Thank you!
ピ
行くぞおら
Let's get going!
Fukunaga!
福永
(山本)ダシャ
Take that!
Nice receive!
ナイスレシブ
≪また速攻≫
Another fast attack!
う
ははははありゃ
拾えなくてもしょうがねぇな
You could hardly expect him to retrieve that.
頼むぜ
(月島)あ
I'm counting on you!
頼んます
おう
I'm counting on you!
Right.
お疲れ
ああざす
Well done.
Thank you.
向こうのリベロヤバいすね
え
Their libero is a threat.
Hinata, let's go!
旭さんのスパイク初めて見るのに
手に当てました
He'd never seen Asahi spike before, but he touched it.
あすみません
I'm sorry!
I'm sorry! Take this!
すみませんこれお願いします
うん
Hinata, you dumbass!
Sure.
Shake it off, guys!
(西谷)ドンマイドンマイ
(黒尾)山本ナイサ
Noya, go for it!
Nishinoya sure switches a lot.
(武田)
西谷君はすぐ交代するんですね
Left!
(菅原)
はい守備専門のリベロは
Yes, sir. Since the libero specializes in defense, they goes on and off the court many times.
何回でも
コトを出入りできます
Net
Front row
Back row
うちは
ミドルブロｯカの日向と月島が
Our middle blockers, Hinata and Tsukishima, go to the rear to serve,
後衛に回りサブを打て
１ラリ終わたところで
and once the rally is done,
they swap positions with Nishinoya.
西谷と交代します
次は俺だ
Now it's my turn!
ふん
ピ
う
く
(烏野一同)よしゃ
とんでもねぇな
Right on!
That's ridiculous.
お
たまらずタイムアウトか
Ooh!
A hasty timeout.
(猫又)リベロもスパイカも
いいのがいるな
They have a good libero and good spikers.
中でもいちばんとんでもねぇのは
セタだ
The most ridiculous of the lot is their setter.
あれは化け物だな
He's a monster.
He quickly sets to the spiker's optimum striking point.
スパイカの最高打点への
最速トス
針の穴を通すコントロルだ
He has the control to thread the needle.
まあ天才はしょうがねぇ
Anyway, you can't do anything about a prodigy.
が天才が一人交じたところで
But they're not gonna win this thing just because they happen to have one prodigy on the team.
それだけじゃ勝てやしないのさ
翔陽が攻撃の軸なら
If Shouyou is their attack axis, we should stop him.
翔陽を止めちゃえばいい
Shouyou?
(山本)翔陽
(黒尾)あのすばしこい１０番
Their nimble number ten.
(猫又)
あの９番と１０番はいわば
Their number nine and number ten...
鬼とその金棒
are like a demon and his iron club.
まずは鬼から金棒を奪う
We'll take the iron club from the demon.
ピ
(烏野一同)おしゃ
Nekoma
Karasuno
Let's do this!
(武田)すごいいい調子ですね
This is great!
They're at their best!
(繋心)なんか気持ち悪いな
え
They give me the willies.
Huh?
(繋心)
様子をうかがわれてるつうか
It's as though they're feeling us out. Like we're being scrutinized.
観察されてるつうか
ぬぅくそ
Dammit!
Nekoma
Karasuno
Shake it off!
(山本)
ドンマイドンマイ惜しかたぞ
You almost had it.
≪あの７番
日向についてきている
I'm sorry!
Their number seven is keeping up with Hinata.
音駒はブロクを
サイドに寄せたな
Nekoma has moved their blockers to the side.
Yeah, a dedicated block.
うんデディケトシフト
≪このブロクエスを
徹底マクするためじゃなくて
This block isn't designed to keep the ace marked.
もしかして
≪日向の動きの誘導
Could it be...
They're attempting to lead Hinata?
(孤爪･((翔陽の動く範囲を
狭くしちゃえばいいよ
Just shrink down Shouyou's movement area.
見た感じ翔陽はただ単に
From what I can tell, Shouyou simply charges to wherever there are no blockers.
ブロクのいない所に
突込んでいくんだ
だからブロクを片方に寄せれば
反対側に動く))
So if we put our blockers on one side, he'll move to the opposite side.
((あとはひたすら追かける))
((はいす
After that, keep following him.
Yes, sir!
((確かにあんな攻撃
最初に見たときは
I think that anyone would be taken by surprise seeing their fast attack for the first time.
誰でもびくりするんだと思う))
((でも最初クリアできそうにない
ゲムでも
In a game, the more you repeat a level you can't pass at first...
繰り返すうちに
慣れるんだよ))
the more you get used to it.
≪１０番を追かける
１０番を追かける≫
Follow number ten. Follow number ten.
ぬ
≪また触た
He touched it again?!
速攻来る
It's a fast attack!
え
くくそ
Damn.
(澤村)ﾄﾞﾝﾏｲﾄﾞﾝﾏｲ
(武田)ツアタク
Shake it off!
A setter dump.
おい力みすぎんなよ
Hey, don't get too tense.
ちょとの隙も見られてる
They can see through the cracks.
(澤村)前
(田中)うお
Forward!
すまんノヤさんカバ頼む
任せろ
I'm sorry, Noya! Cover it!
I've got it!
ライト
え影山がトス呼んだ
Right!
What?! Kageyama called for a set?!
Kageyama, finish it!
影山ラスト
(２人)ええ
おい今のがストレトだからな
サイドライン沿いますぐ
Hey! That was a straight spike!
You go straight along the line.
ちゃんと
打ち分けできるようになれよ
You need to learn to choose your hits!
こいつのハイスペク
マジ腹立つわ
It seriously pisses me off how he's so good at everything.
またくです
You said it.
Nekoma
Karasuno
(福永)あ
(澤村)ナイスタチ月島
Nice tip, Tsukishima!
≪こいつ賢いヤツだ≫
This guy is smart.
He thinks calmly and observes his surroundings.
≪冷静によく見て考えるヤツ
翔陽とは真逆≫
The exact opposite of Shouyou.
ピ
(田中)ナイサ
Nice serve!
Yamamoto!
(黒尾)山本
(山本)よしゃ
All right!
(夜久)ナイスレシブ
Nice receive!
≪誰に上げようかな≫
≪ライトか≫
Which side should I give it to?
The right?
(孤爪)レフトだよ
No, the left.
≪やぱりよく見てた≫
He did watch closely, as I thought.
≪反応も速い≫
And he has fast reflexes.
駒一同)よしゃ
All right!
≪今の視線フェイント
That glance was a decoy!
(猫又)他人が苦手で
他人の目を気にするがゆえ
Because he's not good with people,
he became so self-conscious of where they were looking that he became very observant of their eyes.
他人をよく観察する
あいつは予測がうまい
He's good at predicting his opponents' moves.
He can predict how someone will act based on what their personality is like.
こいつはこういうタイプで
きとこう動くて予測が
でもうちの強さは
そこがポイントじゃないけどな
Although, that isn't what makes our team strong.
Haikyuu !!
(孤爪)＜昔から自分から友達とか
つくれたためしがない＞
I've never had any luck making friends.
＜他人は苦手で
関わりたくないくせに
I wasn't good around people,
so I wanted nothing to do with them.
他人の目はすごく気になる＞
But I became extremely self-conscious of their eyes.
＜目立たないために
神経をとがらせた＞
I didn't let it get to me so that I wouldn't stand out.
＜遊び相手は
年も家も近いクロだけ＞
My only playmate was Kuro,
who was my age and lived nearby.
＜スポツは
特に好きじゃないけど
I don't really like sports,
but I've always fiddled with volleyball.
バレボルは昔から触てた＞
＜中学はクロに言われて
なんとなくバレ部に入た＞
In junior high, Kuro persuaded me to join the volleyball team.
＜ちょと楽しかた＞
It was a little fun.
＜高校でも
またなんとなく続けた＞
In high school, I found myself still playing it.
＜少し前まで
強かた学校だた＞
Our school had a good team not long ago.
＜人がたくさんいた
ここは苦手だと思た＞
There were so many people.
I decided I couldn't handle it.
(部員)((１年片づけ遅ぇよ
帰れねぇだろ
Hey, first-year! You need to clean up faster or we can't go home!
＜先輩というのは１年とか２年
早く生まれただけで
The people we call upperclassmen just happened to be born a year or two before us.
どうして
あんなに威張るんだろう＞
So why do they act so bossy?
((やめんなよ
Don't quit on me.
((お前は
鋭い観察眼を持てるし
You have keen observational skills,
and you deliver accurate instructions.
指示だて的確だ))
The current first-years and second-years know how great you are.
((今の１２年は
お前のすごさを分かている))
((お前は絶対にチムを強くする))
You'll definitely make the team stronger.
(武田)目立たないですね
(繋心)あ
He doesn't stand out.
Huh?
(武田)
うちの影山君は素人が見ても
It's obvious to an amateur that
Kageyama gives off sharp vibes.
すごい感じが
ビシビシ伝わてくるけど
Nekoma's setter might indeed be doing amazing things,
but it's hard to tell by looking at him.
音駒のｾｯﾀｰ君は何かすごいことを
やてるのかもしれないけど
見ててもよく分からない
それは
あの安定したレシブのせいだ
That's due to the consistency of their receiving.
多彩な攻撃を仕掛けるために
何より重要なのは
The most important thing to set up a wide variety of attacks is
セタの頭上に
きれいに返てくる
receives that deliver the ball neatly above the head of the setter.
あのレシブだ
あのレシブがあるから
Those receives enable their setter to utilize his best potential.
向こうのセタは
本領を発揮できてるんだ
セタである影山が
圧倒的才能で
Kageyama is holding together his uncoordinated team with overwhelming talent,
デコボコのチムを繋ぐのが
烏野なら
駒
while Nekoma's setter, Kozume, is supported by the receiving skills of his entire team.
(黒尾)＜俺たちは血液だ＞
We are plasma.
Keep the flow in motion.
＜滞りなく流れろ酸素を回せ
Distribute the oxygen.
脳が正常に働くために＞
So the brain can run smoothly!
く
(犬岡)ワンタチ
(山本)ナイスカバ夜久さん
I touched it!
Nice cover, Yaku!
超人みたいなエｰスがいなくても
We don't need a superman for an ace.
地道に丁寧に
As long as we earn the points one by one, slowly but surely.
１点１点を積み重ねていけば
うおら
Take that!
Nekoma
Karasuno
駒一同)よしゃ
Yeah!
Kageyama, I'm going to make the next spike count, so set for me!
影山次こそバシと決めるから
トスくれ
今相手のセトポイントだ
Right now, it's set point for the opponent.
ミスたらこのセｯト落とすぞ
う
Mess up, and we lose the set.
分かてる決める
I know! I'll do it!
Nice receive!
(田中)ナイスレシブ
In a game, the more you repeat a level you can't pass at first...
((最初クリアできそうにない
ゲムでも
何回も繰り返すうちに
(孤爪)((慣れるんだよ))
the more you get used to it.
Nekoma              Karasuno
駒一同)よしゃ
I finally caught you!
All right!
おい
いちいちへこんでらんねぇぞ
Hey, we can't let each little thing get us down.
次のセト取り返す
We're going to take back the next set!
There's no spike that can't be stopped.
(繋心)絶対に止められない
スパイクなんかないんだ
Don't get distracted.
迷うなよ
(田中)次は決めたれ日向
Let's nail the next one, Hinata!
Smash it in.
(西谷)ガとな
はい
Yes, sir!
Not again.
ああまた
し
Nice block, Inuoka!
(山本)ナイスブロク犬岡
≪あの７番まぐれじゃねぇ≫
Their number seven is no fluke.
He's learning how Hinata moves.
≪日向の動きに慣れてきたんだ≫
Karasuno               Nekoma
(西谷)大地さんナイスカバ
(田中)レフト
Daichi, nice cover!
Left!
(繋心)なんで
日向を交代させないのかて
Tanaka!
Do you want to ask why I don't swap out Hinata?
言いてぇのか
(月島)あ別に
All right!
Not really.
これが公式戦なら代えてるかもな
If this was an official match, I might swap him out.
でも
今なら解決策を探すチャンス
But right now, this is his chance to find the solution.
だが日向が
戦意を喪失してしまうようなら
However, if that results in Hinata losing his will to fight, maybe I should take him out of the match once.
一回下げた方がいいかもな
≪かわした
He's going around!
くそ
(武田)ダメか
Shit!
It's no good!
駒一同)よしゃ
はぁはぁはぁ
All right!
(菅原)≪中学最初で最後の試合で
完全にシャトアウトされて
Completely shut out in the first and last match in junior high.
高校でも
月島の高さに全然勝てなくて
No match for Tsukishima's height in high school.
それでもやと手に入れた
But he finally obtained a way to fight opponents far taller than himself.
自分より
ずとでかい相手と戦う方法
To Hinata, this is his sole, most powerful attack.
日向にとて
唯一で最強の攻撃
それがたた一人のブロカに
止められた≫
All prevented by a single blocker!
気力をくじく人の壁
It's the spirit-breaking "human wall."
The more you hit it, the more your spirit breaks.
打てば打ただけ心は折れて
笑た
He's smiling.
おい
なんか違うんだ
Hey.
It's different somehow.
ブロクで
向こう側が全然見えなくて
It's not the same as back when I felt confused because I couldn't see the other side past the blockers
どうすればいいか
全然分かんなかた
and didn't know what to do.
あのころの感じとは
なんか違う
It's different somehow.
向こうも
ギリギリでついてきてるの分かる
I can tell that my opponent is having trouble keeping up with me.
Until now, I felt fear and hate when I was blocked.
今までブロクは
怖くて嫌なだけだたのに
あいつが目の前に来ると
わくわくするんだ
Now, I get excited when he shows up in front of me.
お前のトスと
あとなんかの工夫で
With your sets and some kind of plan,
I think I can get it past him.
打ち抜けるんじゃないかて
思うんだ
だからもう一回
So please send one more set my way!
俺にトス上げてくれ
当たり前だ
That goes without saying.
ピ
(山本)ナイサ
Karasuno               Nekoma
Give us a nice serve!
は
え
What?
うわ
ピ
今日向トスを
(山口)見ましたね
Hinata was looking at...
...the set.
今まで
ボルは完全に影山に任せて
Until now, he left the ball fully up to Kageyama and just took the swing!
ひたすらフルスイングだたのに
(繋心)タタタタイム
T-Time out!
あおお前のトス
信用してないとかじゃなくてだな
I-It's not like I don't trust your sets...
How can I say it?
なんだろ
何焦てんだお前
Why are you panicking?
(繋心)影山日向にいつもより
Kageyama, I want you to give
slightly weaker sets to Hinata.
少しだけ
柔めのトスを出してやれ
いつもの
ダイレクトデリバリじゃなく
Rather than the usual direct delivery...
Indirect delivery.
インダイレクトデリバリ
んイン
In...
(繋心)いつものズバていう
ますぐな軌道のトスじゃなく
Rather than the usual powerful, straight trajectory set,
it needs to float a little.
少しだけフワとしたトスだ
It might be tricky to change it up this sudden.
いきなり変えろて言われても
難しいかもしんねぇけど
やります
I'll do it.
トスを変えるのはどうして
Why would you have him change the set?
空中で
日向に余裕ができるようにだ
To give Hinata freedom in midair.
A moment ago, Hinata attempted to dodge the blocker in midair.
さき日向は
空中でブロｯクを避けようとした
What?
え
(繋心)あのブロｯクを避ける技を
He probably tried to mimic Kageyama's technique to dodge a blocker.
見よう見まねで
やろうとしたんじゃないか
全然できてはなかたけどな
ははは
Although it was crap.
≪今まで
全然考えないで打てたから
Until now, I've hit the ball without a thought in my head, so it's confusing to suddenly be the one aligning the shot!
いざ自分で合わそうとすると
分かんねぇ≫
Karasuno               Nekoma
(繋心)もかいタイム
One more timeout!
Hinata, you need to calm down.
(繋心)日向一回落ち着け
はい
Yes, sir!
I'm sorry. I keep making mistakes.
すすみません
俺ミスたくさん
(田中)何を言うか
俺はいつもお前のおかげで
Go on!
I always get to hit the ball unmarked thanks to you!
フリで打ててるからな
たまには俺の方が
I think I'm allowed to totally own a match once in a while!
カコいい試合が
あたていいんだ
(西谷)
旭さんの方が決めてるけどな
Although Asahi is scoring more points than you!
You shaddup! Anyway, it's all good!
(田中)うるせぇ
とにかくいいんだね旭さん
Right, Asahi?
(東峰)あうんそうそう
Uh, yeah. He's right.
点は俺たちが取り返す
あ
We'll make back the points.
あんまやらかすと
代えられちゃうかもだけどね
If you keep screwing up, you could be swapped out.
ぐ
月島
Tsukishima!
何かつかめそうなら
とことんやりな
If you're on the verge of learning something, keep at it.
跳んでるときは一人でも
後ろにはちゃんと俺たちがいるし
You jump alone,
but we're all here, right behind you.
点はエスが
取り返してくれるらしいしな
After all, the ace claims he's going to win back all those points.
(菅原)大地
旭にプレシャかけんなよ
Daichi, don't put pressure on Asahi!
傷ついちゃたらどうすんだ
(西谷)そうですよ
You wouldn't wanna damage him.
That's right! His heart is very fragile!
ガラスのハトなんだから
(東峰)おお
Please make it stop!
(田中)もうやめてあげて
旭さん
Asahi!
(東峰)レフト
(山口)行け
Left!
Go!
(縁下)ナイスコス
Nice hit!
Karasuno               Nekoma
Aw, it's all he can do to return it.
ああまた返すので精一杯
どうすれば
うまくいくんでしょうね
What would it take to make it go smoother?
初めてのプレを
すぐできないのなんて当然だ
Nobody can be expected to get a play right the first time.
Nice receive!
Send it my way!
But the initial effort is the beginning in all things.
でもどんなことだて
｢やてみる｣から始まるんだ
小さな巨人て
前に烏野にいたろ
Remember how the Little Giant used to play for Karasuno?
日向君憧れのエスですね
Hinata's dream ace?
名前のまんまだけど
身長は１７０センチそこそこで
True to his name, he stood at around 170 cm,
and at first, he kept being stopped by blockers.
最初はブロクに
止められてばかだた
それが２年の後半には
But by the latter half of his second year, no one could match him in aerial battle.
空中戦で
右に出るヤツはいなくなた
ブロクの高さにかなわないなら
その隙間を狙て打つ
He couldn't compete with the high blockers, so he aimed for the gap and fired.
わざとブロクの指先に当てて
はじき飛ばす
He would intentionally hit the blockers' fingertips and make it ricochet.
そうやて小柄な自分の
戦える道を作ていたんだ
That's how he found a way for a smaller guy like himself to fight.
全部うちのじいさんから
聞いた話だけどな
At least, that's according to what my gramps told me.
烏養前監督ですか
(繋心)ああ
You mean the previous Coach Ukai?
Yeah. I remember what my gramps told me very clearly.
じいさんが言てたことを
すげぇよく覚えてる
(烏養)((翼がないから
人は飛び方を探すのだ))
Man doesn't have wings,
so he finds a way to fly.
ピ
ああアウトか
Aw! It's out!
すげぇ
That was amazing!
That was amazing, Shouyou!
すげぇな翔陽
はぁはぁもう一回
One more time!
Next Episode Preview
Your resident small fry... Is his name Hinata?
(黒尾)おたくのチビちゃん
日向君だけ
He's pretty amazing, even though that last one was out.
すごいねぇ
最後アウトだたけど
Not at all. He's nothing compared to your resident Inuoka.
(澤村)いやいや
おたくの犬岡君には負けますよ
普通に敵に感動してたけど
Even though he's always wowed by the opponent.
Excuse me, but you guys are scaring me.
(菅原)
あのなんか怖いんですけど
Episode Thirteen:
Worthy Adversaries
Next time on Haikyuu!!:
"Worthy Adversaries."